this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
as a radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every two
weeks thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
supporting the program
welcome listeners to a new episode of
software engineering radio this one is
about spring and my guest is Everard
wolf
hello ever hot hi of course now that
ever hop I mean some of you might know
remember back in the old days ages ago
Everhart was part of the SA radio team
and of course at that time we never
could really talk about spring because
we didn't you know now we can do it
because he's not on the team anymore
so so this is an episode about spring
and obviously we try to focus on the
technologies behind it and why spring is
interesting so but before we do that
about please for those that have
forgotten who you are please introduce
yourself again to our listeners okay so
first of all thanks for having me on
on the show it's really an honor and I
still feel somewhat said that I had to
quit AC radio because well there was was
just too much stuff that I said I had to
do okay so my name is David Wolfe I am
the regional director for Strings was in
the german-speaking area which is
Germany Austria and the german-speaking
part of Switzerland so I'm running the
operations there and the other role that
I have is I'm a principal canet Springs
house so I do trainings consulting
reviews and all that kind of stuff so
that's why I come from okay so well I
guess we should start with giving people
an overview about what what spring is
not about not in every detail but just
like 10,000 foot oh you yeah so
basically spring is a framework and it
contains of three parts first of all
there is dependency injection then there
is a opie and the last part is service
abstraction layer so let's let me
elaborate on those parts a little bit so
dependency injections basically a
technique that allows you to make
objects know each other while while
usually you would have a factory pattern
for example to do that and it
fancy injections it's just set methods
or constructor parameters that are
filled up with references to other
objects and there is the framework magic
behind that does that yeah exactly and
the reason why this is a good thing is
first of all it allows you to exchange
those dependent objects for mocks if you
wanted to testing and the other thing is
that some things like for example if you
want to get access to J in the eye which
is a naming system that is used in Java
EE environments in particular you can
hide away the details of such a system
by just injecting some objects and you
don't have to care with the details of
these of these techniques so it's
actually interchangeable you can get
objects from train the eye or plane you
can use plain Java objects and for that
reason applications also become more
portable so you can run them on Java EE
or on Tomcat
or in your simple environment that
you're using for simple tests so
fundamentally I mean spring is let's say
an alternative framework for enterprise
Enterprise II kind of distributed java
applications the questions
alternative to watch so also the
official standards like je t'ai be these
kinds of things
well you can't integrate spring and in
some areas I would argue that it's
actually competitor they are competing
against each other so for example there
are also dependency injection
technologies in hb3 for example but
spring is more powerful and also you can
integrate it so I mean you can still run
your applications on Java EE servers
right if you're using spring so let me
revisit that spring is an alternative
programming model for building
enterprise applications that may or may
not run on the infrastructure provided
by je yeah and I think we did an episode
a long time ago on enterprise stuff I
think the future of enterprise Java and
you came up with this term the
enterprise operating system or something
you know the applications of which
provides the runtime infrastructure
which is independent from program model
yeah I mean the the the important part
and what you have to think about is that
Java EE is first of all not the
predominant approach anymore because if
you look at what people are really using
out there most of the people are using
Tomcat which is not a full Java
implementation anymore yeah and the
other thing that you have to think about
is that a lot of people are stuck with
old java ee service because operations
says well you know we can't just do
every update and some vendors are even
quite conservative in terms of the
standards that they support so I think
one of the the the things that make
spring quite interesting is that it
allows you to use more advanced features
even on those rather old application
servers it's because you have the
separation of programming model which
involves while keeping it compatible on
the service provider side to old
implementations of je yeah exactly and
that's why we have quite a few customers
that are using Java EE service but want
to use the spring programming model in
instead so you talked about dependency
injection the other two you mentioned
where AOP and template on them is it yep
okay all right so I guess we've had
episodes on AOP so I guess you don't
have to explain in detail what IOP is
but how does it relate into spring well
the the idea is that you can you and
that you can use it to implement things
like transactions or as security and add
it to your to your business code and
transparently the AOP implementation in
spring is nowadays compatible to aspectj
so you can easily migrate your own
aspects to a spectra if you want and for
this huge amount of people who have
systems real systems both with aspectj
but the number it's actually the other
way around
so I mean you'll start using spring they
take a look at
P and say well that's actually nice and
then is sometimes they say well but it's
it's limited so we rather than want to
go for a spectra so and and I think that
actually helps the adoption of a spectra
somewhat so it's it's sort of a win-win
situation there
so it appears basically for prospering
Bayeux P is the common ground on which
translate decorative transactions
security and all that kind of stuff is
built on and it allows you to build your
own similar features as well using the
same techniques so the granularity for
the AOP is probably the spring beam
where a spring beam is let's say the
smallest managed entity managed by
spring yeah even though you can stretch
this concept quite considerably so if
you look at spring security for example
what you obviously want to do is you
want to have specific domain model
instances that are only accessible to
certain users and with domain model you
don't mean managed beans that provide
services but rather data classes yeah so
you let's say you have a customer
service that would be a managed spring
managed bean yeah and the customer
service returns from customers and you
must not see the customers that don't
belong to your region right and you can
actually implement that using spring AOP
because what you just do is you target
the customer service and you filter the
results of each method call where are
the customers that you you don't have to
see so the aspect still advise the
service and not the domain objects yeah
what would I do if I would want to say I
can only see three of the five
attributes of the customer can I also
advise domain objects or I mean I can do
with respect to a low level wise but is
there a way in spring to do this
systematically or would I just revert
back to AOP in the sense of aspectj well
I mean what you could still do is you
could still try to use the same trick
that says okay you you stick to the to
the services and you do additional stuff
to the domain model you could do
you will remove the contents of those
fields when you hand them out yeah
which might have nice effects if those
domain objects are managed by hibernate
for example because they a change
objects might be written to the database
but yeah the in particular if you wanted
to add aspects to your domain model I
usually advise that you should think
about using a spectra because especially
these rather fine-grained aspects are
more efficient if you use spectra and
you also have a lot more that you can
actually advise so the it is just more
powerful yeah because the advices are
not limited or actually I should say the
join point model is not just the beam
boundary but rather all-day low-level
tell about grammar everything yeah so so
basically the as you said using spring
AOP what you can do is you can advise
spring means yeah and change them using
aspectj
you can change everything that somehow
runs in the JVM and the way it works is
that you either have load time weaving
so you do some manipulation on the class
loader there is actually support for
this kind of abstraction in spring so
spring can help you to tweak your class
order to do that or you use different
compilers for the a spectral compiler so
that's that's sort of the trade-off so
if you get spring you have spring our
AOP out of the box which is so it's
easier to use in that respect because if
you just use spring and your spring AOP
out of the box while if you want to go
for the more powerful model you would
have to change the compiler or tweak the
class loader which is for some people a
hurdle so but then you could use a
spectrum that's the idea tend to think
that from from a design perspective it
is it is useful to try to limit the AOP
magic to component boundaries but I mean
that's just my opinion
that's actually an interesting topic
because what I mean in particular in
training horrified
about spring I get a lot of questions
around well how do you keep your aspects
from messing up the code and my
impression is that what you can be using
AOP is that you can add specific
behavior to certain parts of your
architecture so you would say well every
service that I define will have a
security check every Dao that I defined
will have a certain transaction behavior
and if you use that approach I can't see
how you can actually mess up your code
using aspects because at the end of the
day it that would just mean that you're
not you don't know what what your
architecture is like so that's basically
my idea about that okay so the third
ingredient fundamental basic ingredient
of spring in addition to dependency
injection AOP which we talked about was
the template pattern what's not yeah
that is part of the enterprise service
abstraction that is in spring it's
probably the most important part so the
idea of the template pattern is that you
pass in certain code that should be
executed and this code then gets some
resources like a JDBC connection a JDBC
statement or a JMS resource or whatever
and executes using that resource and you
don't have to clean up the resources
little bit like as if you could pass if
you had closures then you would pass in
a closure to a service method that exits
that is I want to talk about yeah
emulation for closures kind of it's not
about it's not about the closures I mean
the emulation of closures in right in in
Java or PCI in our classes yes or
anonymous inner classes it is an
environment that allows you to use those
to pass in resources to such let's say
closures or in a class or whatever and
through that you don't have to handle
those resources yourself okay I mean
it's it's quite interesting to take a
look at for example 280 BC not
long ago I've read a tutorial in a
magazine for JDBC and it didn't talk
about how you can probably clean up your
resources and in real life in real
enterprise applications that's a big
no-no because you will end up with
resource leaks and your application will
sooner or later
well not work anymore um generally but
these template patents are just part of
the general abstraction so we have some
more abstractions there for example
there is a common abstraction for all
the transaction api's that are out there
I mean it's quite interesting to see
that a simple thing like a transaction
that is basically just to commit and or
a robic plus a begin it can be done in
so many different ways as we have it in
the Java platform right now so there is
there is an abstraction layer there as
well to sort of clean up the the mess
that is that has been created there and
so on and so on one way of doing that as
I understand it is the use of
annotations
I mean classically you would have
written a beans XML a configuration file
that basically specifies which instances
of which types you have and how they're
injected in the sense of dependency
injection more recently you have gone
over to the annotations side so so can
you explain a little bit which role
annotations play in regard to dependency
action and also regard ILP oh yeah sure
so what we've done in Spring 2.5 is
support for annotations for dependency
injection was added as you mentioned so
you can annotate a class and say well
this is a spring bean so it will
automatically be instance the editor so
spring mean and you can also define the
borrowing between the beans using
annotations this is not unparalleled I
mean it should be fresh or it should be
three has as similar features it is yeah
interesting to note that a lot of people
still stick to X XML and one of the main
reasons they gave give is that
have configuration files that sort of
gives them an idea about the structure
of the application which I find
interesting because in a lot of key well
you could argue if you have let's say a
service plan interface plus an
implementation it's quite easy to guess
what will be injected if you want to get
access to an instance of the service
interface it's going to be the service
implementation so it's not I mean it's
not that hard to guess that and that's
what what probably the XML will will
contain off but anyway I mean we have
added this annotation support it's an
alternative I wouldn't say it's it's
better or worse than what we have in
index in XML it's just a different
approach and using in in AOP you can use
AOP for you can use annotations for the
point cuts so you would advise all
classes or methods that have the
following annotation yep so and I think
that's basically what it boils down to I
think what it boils down to is you can
define your eyes texture so you can say
well the service is something that is
annotated as at service and then you
would say okay well ap will add security
transactions and spring dependency
injection container world turn that into
a spring bean but you might as well do
the same thing using naming conventions
so you could say everything that where
the class name ends since have simple oh
yeah
the difference is of course that
annotations are their own types so you
get some type check if you have a typo
in your Impa thing suffix beer sure
nothing happens if you mention an
annotation it doesn't exist you get a
compiler or so it's a better typing I'm
not saying that something that one of
these approaches is better okay what
what I'm basically trying to say is
Springs about flexibility so if you want
to go for annotation right behind if you
don't want to do it there are
alternatives that so but you also use
annotation
and I guess we'll talk about that later
if you talk about the spring universe as
you've called it you also use
annotations as a way to mark up spring
beans with all kinds of additional
information that then is used by various
frameworks like web service rest or
something else where you look at the
annotations and then the framework does
some magic behind it may be implemented
as AOP maybe not mm well there are if
you look at spring integration for
example there are some annotations that
I defined there there are obviously some
senator nations like in jax-rs for
example but the doctorís that's that's
standard for rest implementations in in
the Java world and but those are I mean
those are evaluated not by spring hall
but rather by these other frameworks
that projects RS or spring integration
or whatever so I guess we've we've
covered the core of spring I think we
should take a look at Spring universe
can you give us a couple of
representative examples of additional
spring facilities on top of the the core
framework yeah basically what what has
happened and that's an ongoing process
for quite some while is that we thought
that there are other areas in the Java
world that also could be done
differently better or where we have a
specific approach and that ended up in
creating more and different projects
that are somehow related to spring they
often do use the the container but in
some cases like spring security for
example and you can actually use it
without using spring itself so Springs
security for example can also be used
with a spec J or without any AOP
implementation whatsoever or based on
just softer filters so it's actually a
little bit more flexible but basically
you're right it's it's stuff that has
been added to to spring to take care of
specific areas so let's walk
for a couple of examples I think let's
start with one that's maybe not so hyped
because nobody talks about batch
processing but you have a module or ago
how do you how do you call these things
Aran's modules projects projects called
spring batch yeah what's that what's the
architectural abstractions behind better
processing as you see it in spring batch
what is the challenge in batch
processing maybe should say that way
yeah probably we are too young to
realize where where the issues are so I
think spring batches is it's one of the
the more interesting projects because it
fills a gap that is actually very
apparent if you think about it and it's
very interesting to a lot of companies
because there is batch processing there
will always be better processing and
there are quite a few projects based on
Java that wanna do better processing to
switch off mainframes but also because
the the things they are doing are done
daily so they have to do it in a batch
or they have to print out invoices and
you can only do that sensible in a batch
and so on and so on so I think it's it's
a very interesting thing that nobody had
the idea to support that kind of stuff
before we get that so you asked about
the abstractions that are there and so
basically one of the the issues around
batch processing a are first of all that
there are some optimizations so you
don't want to do a commit for each and
every data set but you rather want to
pile them together and do a commit for
em I don't know ten hundred thousand or
so and the reason for that is because
the transaction on the database is
somewhat of an overhead or adds quite
some processing time to the database and
and if you want to do if you want to
implement your batches in a performant
way you can't you just can't commit each
and every data set that's just not
possible so that's one example the other
thing that is pretty hard if you don't
framework that helps you is a restart
ability so if your system crashes and
it's a one-hour batch you have to
somehow be able to restart your
application there are obvious ways how
you do that so I mean you can stall the
status of your batch in the database and
then restart the batch from that
specific point so that's also
automatically supported in our spring
batch and another thing is a parallel
processing so you want to do part of the
batch in parallel multiple parts
parallel to become more efficient or
faster if your system is scalable then
you get more performance if you do more
stuff in parallel and that's something
that has been added in spring 2.0 so so
one thing one problem you have if you
have interactive applications on one
side and batch job applications on the
other side is that you sometimes have to
duplicate business logic because in the
interactive case you you basically write
the code so that it handles only one
case and in a batch for example you do
it you do about the update right and
then if you do it about the update with
an SQL statement that's custom-made then
you kind of bypass certain application
logic that you've put into your beans
through which you would normally go so
is there any support to resolve that
problem will the batch processing also
use the services defined in the beans or
I mean I think that's one of the central
issues isn't that with batch it is
certainly one of the interesting issues
around batches and what you can
obviously do is you can use the same
business logic for online as well as bad
and in one case you would just use it
using I don't know spring and we see or
something some web front-end and in the
other case you would run the same logic
using spring batch but it would still
mean that let's say I have let's say I
have customers and I want to update
their status to be X for all customers
that have paid an invoice this month
okay so you would do this as if you did
it in real that processing you right you
would write one SQL statement
right whereas if you do it with spring
batch going through the services what
will happen on the databases that will
be probably first you get a cursor or
you know set of data objects and then
you update them sequentially each one at
one at at the point at a time so so
there's no way around that is there um
well to give the tripplehorns an answer
it abates yeah so if you look at
hibernate for example what it does is it
it does batch updates and it does them
if you close the session which in spring
is by the end of a transaction okay so
using the spring entrance the the spring
batch transaction integration you would
do a batch update by the end of the
transaction we put which would contain
all the different or the different items
that you've touched during that
transaction okay so technically speaking
there are ways to do that and in
particular if you have a separate
business persistence layer it should be
easy to do that in other words you would
rely on the persistence layer to detect
that there is a bunch of updates that
could be done in one you know fell swoop
instead of doing them or add something
at some special case so if you have a
tray to be see base positions they would
probably add at a specific case however
I mean what you are assuming and I think
that's the interesting part what you're
assuming is that the same business logic
is executed in batch and online well not
really same business logic because the
use cases are obviously different
otherwise you wouldn't have it but the
same constrains the same checks the same
consistency rules and so on
probably but and I'm not sure I mean
I've done some some batch processing
even before joining spring sauce using
Java and I'm not sure whether that's
actually really the case okay
and if you think about it I mean if
there is if let's say you have an online
shop so someone
issues an order in your online shop
you're probably going to do quite a lot
of checks that say well it's the credit
card valid is the address valid and I
don't know what else and yeah you were
also you will also give the customer
some feedback that says well you know
this is not really it's not on stock so
you have to think about something
different here or here's an alternative
and whatever and particularly this thing
about the alternatives and the decision
that the customer might make is just not
an option in bed so yeah so I'm actually
wondering and I think that it depends on
the case at hand yeah whether the idea
that you can use the same business logic
is actually true not so much because of
technical constraints I would think that
you can somehow work around those but
I'm really very wondering whether it's
the same functionality that yeah and I
guess if you have certain constraints
that need to apply in both cases then
putting them into the database the
database if possible is one way to go
but okay anyways another module that or
whatever another thing that I find very
interesting is DM dynamic modules the
integration between spring and OSGi um
we've had an episode on OSGi I guess for
our discussion here we can define it as
a fancy modular class loader or is that
isn't that doing it justice well I would
I think it's it's two parts so basically
the ideas that you modernize your
systems into bundles that's basically
draw files with some specific stuff so
and with module I think modular right
the term is is ambiguous because you're
the beans already modular is your system
various application context also do it
so it's a runtime modularization isn't
it well we should talk about that later
on
basically the ideas that you have a set
of classes like in an Eclipse project
that would and the result of that would
be a bundle and this bundle might import
or export specific packages right okay
and the other thing that you can do is
you can export and import services so
it's just basically object okay so it's
it's a higher level visibility mechanism
on top of java packages yeah and then
there is the fact that at runtime you
can dynamically load and unload those
bundles that also serve okay exactly but
the main point is there are bundles
bundles might import/export right
packages or services right so and which
of those two features that we just
mentioned is exploited in spring diem
well let's export an import of services
and packages so it's actually four
features okay anyway and so the most
important part I think or how it fits
into the spring picture is using spring
and spring dependency injection in
particular you can define how objects
are wired together and the problem is
it's done in a flat namespace but you
could work around somehow and there are
also no clear visibility routes so you
can't say this has been that I want to
export to a different pair to a
different bundle or whatever to a
different module and this is my private
inner being you must not use this which
is key as you probably agree to a proper
component system so the way this works
the all the basically the idea is well
we have bundles each of those bundles
has its own spring configuration its own
application context there are some beans
that are public and there they will be
exported to other bundles and there are
some beans that will be coming out with
GI service exactly so basically those
sort of public beans are the O's giant
services and you can also consume most
joy services so by that you can wire
together your system of bundles and if
those sort of public beans let's take a
look at the situation within one bundle
okay you say within one bundle there is
one application configuration which
means that within this one bundle you
have the usual spring dependency
injection no questions asked right now
we have two bundles and there is the one
bundle let's call it B which export with
which makes a couple of its beans
public as OSGi services how does the
other bundle a how does dependency
injection work with those services will
it inject the service references into
those beans or how do you how does this
work
so the way it works is that a proxy is
generated and this proxy is injected so
and that's actually quite nice because
um the problem as you mentioned is the
pundits might be installed on and
started runtime yes this whole dynamic
world view everything can go and come as
it ends and the way by using this proxy
approach what you can do is if your
service all of sun disappears
you just buffer the method calls to that
service and wait until the service
reappears
but that's hopefully configurable well
sure you could you could also define a
timeout if you want you but that's
that's basically one of the parts right
but the other thing that is interesting
here is um if you are smart enough you
can actually build a configuration that
allows you to run the system with or
without all those GI so the way it works
let's assume the responder that exports
let's say customer Dao to access
customers in the database and there's
another bundle that has a customer
service that uses this customer deal the
way it usually works would be that the
customer service has a reference to a
spring beam that is such a nosy I
proceed and then the customer Dao is
exported as such a knows Jaya service
what you can do if you as I mentioned if
you're smart enough is you can leave out
the middle part that exports and imports
your service and you just stick together
the O's GI the the customer service and
the estimate ei o directly and that way
you don't have the the proxy the
property you don't have the proxy and
you don't also don't have the the
dynamics anymore right but your system
still works and you could run it on Java
EE if you want to are on a simple Tomcat
if you want to so that's also quite cool
I would argue yeah so so so it's always
- I have to say this is it is it is it
just an add-on or is it something that
you guys consider a really useful and
important ingredient kind of you know
because I mean spring doesn't do
anything about the runtime dynamics
whereas OSGi does you know so I think
it's a nice compliment so yeah
absolutely I mean if you look at at what
we are doing right now
so what spring sauce has done is we have
added support form we we have commercial
support for Tomcat now and we have a
version of Tomcat that is actually good
for for logic test installations that's
sort of the traditional runtime
environment that you could use for your
spring applications or any other
applications that you want to which is
sort of a Bay sort of a limited Java EE
implementation because it just sticks to
surf light so it's more lightweight the
other thing that we have and that's
that's important concerning usgi is the
sort of next generation runtime
environment which is the DM server that
is based on those joy based on dynamic
modules and adds some more stuff like
support for a hibernate is some other
advanced features support for load time
leaving and so on and so on and that's
also an open source project and it
actually proves or it actually tells
what we think how important was joyous
we have also another initiative to put
out OCI compatible versions of a lot of
libraries that that we offer
so in some sense you're you're replacing
let's say hae based runtime environment
with a noise GI base runtime environment
we offer there is an optimum and my
question would be that je does a lot
more than more or less dynamic modular
ization
it also comes with
load-balancing if you do it the right
way it provides monitoring and other
things that you get as part of an
application service
oh it really doesn't have that so do my
question is do you position OSGi and je
as competitors in the same space or do
you say there are some environments
where you need the big fat je and then
it's good that there is there that it is
there and for more lightweight
environments you use the OSGi runtime or
what's your well team and so to take the
concrete things that you've just
mentioned so load load balancing is not
not a problem because the M server has
Tomcat and I think okay the the
scalability of Tomcat is is well known
we also provide monitoring support for
that for the M server so there are there
are parts of that
once you've rebelled and applications
are on top of it so SGI yeah it's which
is which is focused on web because again
the important thing is if you look at
the statistics most of the projects I
think 70% or so are done on a pure
Tomcat environment so the reality is
that Java EE is not the dominant
application platform anymore
yeah that's just not what we see unless
you count a pure servlet implementation
as je and it's seniority is 10 to 2 and
even even if you look at the full-blown
Java EE servers in a lot of cases they
are just used as africana so what it
boils down to is that we think that
you're much better off using these
lightweight environments because they're
easier to administrate it easier to work
with and that's what we are focusing on
there are of course some minor cases
where a travel server might might add
value but the broad I mean the broad
majority of people is not using Java
server anymore it's just not what they
are doing so since we're
talking about the web already there is
also support for web applications
specifically in spring and what I find
interesting is that not just is there a
huge load of web frameworks in general
in the Java world there is even a huge
load of web frameworks but in spring so
which one is the the one that should be
primarily used today and how do they
play together and I would argue that
again the consulting answer is it
depends so I think there is a variety in
web frameworks in the Java space for a
reason and they are tied to specific to
specific cases first of all let me let
me say that spring actually has support
for quite a few web frameworks so if you
don't want to use our own web frameworks
that perfectly fine you can still use
spring for dependency injection
Europeans own our own web framework so
first of all the spring MVC which is
Model View controller framework much
like struts basically a request comes in
is the controller handles the requests
fields up data into the mortal and that
is then rendered by the view which is
more or less what struts also does so
it's in the tradition of struts but with
a much easier and better approach I
would argue the other sort of basic
technology that is out there that we
think actually makes sense is or that we
directly support let me put it rather
put it that way
is a JSF because it's a component based
model so JSF and you have components
like a button or an entry some some text
field or something and you have beans
that handle events that are done on
those widgets which is pretty much what
you do in swing as well and that's a
better alternative if you want to go for
Rich if you want to go for for rich
environments so so what the spring face
is at today is F yes spring faces it's
actually twofold so
first of all it's an integration between
spring javis between JSF and spring web
flow as we will as I will explain later
on the other part of spring phases is a
component library that is based on
spring JavaScript and that spring
JavaScript allows you to add to add
decorations to widgets to a normal HTML
which is basically for validation and
for it pop-ups
yeah basically that's it and based on
that we have spring phases which has
some recive like components for that and
there is also so basically so if you
look at at the frameworks or our view on
the frameworks basically there is
request/response
simple stuff that you would do using
spring MVC and spring MVC is enormously
flexible so it's also the basis for the
integration of web services and so on
into spring and then there is the
component based approach and JSF which
has a different a different area of
excellence and then on top of that you
can add spring web flow to model flows
so multiple pages that can build upon
each other and the nice thing about
spring web flow is first of all you can
actually define those flows as a
first-class citizen so you can you even
have a graphic editor for that and there
is also also variables can be stored in
the flow so it's quite easy to have a
two browser tabs and handle an order in
each of them
it's a different one and they don't
interfere with each other and you can
also add the back button for a back part
and handling is much easier and so on so
like a conversation kind of things yep
the difference is in conversations
usually just an API that says here the
conversation starts here the
conversation ends in spring web flow the
idea is that you have a flow that you
can even model in a in a graphical way
and the conversation is is just well
naturally a part of that flow of law so
it's I would argue it's it's more
elegant to do it that way but I'm biased
but everybody knows that you're biased
so well I actually ever hop is biased
don't believe any word he says so well I
guess there are there is one big topic
we didn't talk about and that's the web
service isn't rests all right remote
communication general I remember that
back in the days when I used to bring
you could export any spring bean using a
number of frameworks and make them
remotely accessible and I guess in the
enterprise space remotely accessible
these days means web services arrest
talk about that yeah sure so there are
two so the rest support is actually
something that we've added to spring MVC
which was part of spring call in 3.0 or
let's say that we are currently editing
adding there it is what I think is quite
interesting there is that it's a very
simple addition to what we already had
in spring MVC so if there are some
fundamental parts in spring and we see
that now pay off so for example a spring
MVC has it's quite flexible in terms of
how it of how it renders a model so
using spring MVC you can render model as
an Excel spreadsheet or as PDF or
whatever and you for the rest of our
that's quite nice because unrest the
ideas that you can access data and you
can have it returned as trays and
rss/atom xml or whatever and it's quite
easy so there is a class now added that
is called condom negotiating if you
resolver that allows you to to render
specific view based on the accept header
or the file extension of the UL so being
basically a Content item like FML text
we have then that kind of stuff
something that that is able to render
some HTML response basically or HTTP
response all right
and the other thing that we added is is
in a notation that allows you to extract
parts of the UL and put that into one of
your method parameters for a title again
yeah so you can annotate the parameter
method parameter and say well please add
the last part of the UL here so if you
have a get for I don't know some UL
customer 42 then you would get the 42
into the parameter and that makes it
quite easy to build rest based systems
then so that's what we are going to do
in spring MVC 3.0 and I think it's it's
interesting to see how if you have the
right abstractions new new features like
Resurrection not that hard
well I'm not that hard to add hour but
they they fit nicely into this model
India exactly so that's what we are
doing there you also talked about spring
Web Services spring Web Services is
actually a separate project and the
reason why we didn't stick to the
existing spring to the existing web
services systems is because we wanted to
focus a lot on contract first web
services so what you do using spring Web
Services is you define the contract
between the client and the server using
XML schema not with stall and the last
thing about and the Basu can be
generated from this XML schema based
sort of data definition but that means
that the whistle is basically only say I
accept an instance of that schema and I
rip right yeah because yeah but the nice
thing is that you don't have to write
this whistle overhead anymore and
they're not the other nice thing is that
you're independent from soap so I mean
you could use the same XML schema to
validate rest as well or you could use
it to to send some XML over JMS or
whatever right exactly I mean that's the
point
I mean web services these days is
basically eight
ttp based XML messaging okay you define
your messages as XML schemas and then
you exchange them using HTTP and s you
say you could just as well exchange them
using any other team S or something else
so I think it's good at agree and about
whistle and that this dope stuff yeah
exactly and that's that sort of the what
makes spring web source unique that it
produces you call it spring XML
messaging I mean seriously I mean isn't
that what it is at its core or am I
missing something maybe because of
marketing reason I don't that's I I yeah
I mean at the end of the day it's still
a tool to implement web services so I
think the the name is actually quite
nice so so yeah what yeah so I guess I
have one more question that I would like
to put at the end so it's there is there
anything else that we forgot to talk
about anything else that's coming up
that you maybe want to mention okay so
let me let me see the thing so we've
talked about spring security somewhat so
basically the idea here there is to add
security to you have applications using
AOP or spring or software filters which
makes it the only one of I think even
the only framework that allows you to do
that to keep your code clean from
security issues and adding them later on
or as a separate aspect which I find
interesting because I mean IOPS is
pretty well I think one of the good use
cases for for AOP I think absolutely and
that's why I'm a little bit I'm yeah a
little bit confused that there are not
too many other frameworks that do that
then we have spring integration that
allows you to do to do integration logic
so well there is this book from by by
Craig or hope and I think you already
had him on the shows integration
patterns yeah and basically what this
what this framework does is it gives you
a way to implement those patterns and
the the that is all based on pipes and
filters basically right
so there are pipes that handle messages
and the filters or pipes that send
messages and filters that handle them
and process them in some way and that's
also the sort of metaphor that is in
spring integration and the pipes in that
case are in a JVM so in the simple case
it's just a method called that is
directly passed through or they might
also be a synchronous Li and there are
adapters for outside JMS file HTTP I
don't know other approaches so that's
sort of yeah basically overview of the
spring universe I'm not sure whether we
forget anything so shall we continue -
what has changed so what currently at
the time of this recording where is due
no July 7 2009 you know still work is
still underway on spring 3.0 the new
stuff in spring 3.0 will be rest as we
already mentioned then there is CL
expression language so that's actually
somewhat of an interesting story because
it's one of the very first enhancement
requests that spring ever got was to add
some kind of a l support into spring so
that you don't have to just configure
well basic string literals on numbers or
in stuff like that but rather advanced
things like yeah well ER expressions so
in other in other words if you have an
XML file that specifies what to inject
into a beam then the string you put
there can be an expression in the L
that's then interpreted by the L
interpreter interpreter as part of the
injection process exactly so what you
could for example do is if there is a
data source a database connection pool
the JDBC URL you could write any L
expression that says take something from
the system properties so and then or
take value X from some separate beam or
whatever
that's basically the idea I think that's
going to add quite a few interesting use
cases because it changes the
fundamentals of how spring
configurations can be written right so
that's that's the idea there then we
will add support for model validation
based on just our 303 so that you can
annotate your domain classes and if you
display your domain objects using a
spring MVC on the web you will get a
validation below curve based on those
what would be an example for such an
annotation to the other day it's like
integer range must be between zero and
three things like on not in not null
right okay name must not be null okay
and then you get a message on the web
front-end that says well the name was
not right not a good idea um
we will support JDK Java 5 plus so
support for jdk 1.4 will be dropped
because that has been end-of-life we
have some new stuff so first of all
there is spring there used to be a
project called spring Java conflict the
idea of Springs over conflict was to
basically take the XML file and do the
same thing using Java do you mean like
in EJB 1.0 you'll remember when you
wrote the deployment descriptors in Java
no you never did that I mean they were
still diced raw objects right yeah I saw
a code subset transactions no we we I
mean the one of the I did the office of
offspring the origin also the offspring
wrote this nice book about j2ee without
e2b which is what is happening right now
right I mean people are using Tomcat and
HP containers anymore so they won't make
the same mistakes no okay no I'm pretty
certain they want so yeah the idea there
is that it sort of looks like a factory
what what you're implementing so you're
generating some code that says well
and generate the data sauce please and I
said I don't know the user name to
something return the whole thing wire
together on the DAO and so on but the
spring bean semantics still applies so
if you define something as a singleton
it will only be created once if you say
this should be done lazily or if you say
this should be in a specific scope let
like the HTTP session for example that
will also be taken into account and
that's well the sort of third
alternative to to configuration the
third basic alternative that will be
there in spring exile and Java program
yeah and that's basically it there is
one minor feature that I think is quite
cool and also also continuous this theme
about that you must know what your
architectures like to use spring
probably so that's the concept of meta
meta annotations so if you if you do
your development in Java nowadays it's
sometimes happens that there are
actually more annotations than real Java
code and the reason for that is that
actually some some annotations just
belong together if you are defining
service as I mentioned you will probably
want to have security checks
transactions and you want to make it a
spring bean you want to have to say you
probably want to have a specific scope
and what was added is something that is
called meta annotations so what you do
is and and I guess you like that
expression just because it says matter
so I think it's not a very good name but
okay yeah whatever grows em well it's
annotations annotations so what you do
is you define your annotation called my
own personal service and you annotate my
own personal service with a
transactional yeah add component and
other spring annotations and every time
you use at my cool service it will be
treated as if all the annotations would
be present on that sauce and the reason
why I said it's more like macros
is that those annotations you annotate
to your own annotation they don't affect
the annotation you write but rather if
you apply your own annotation to a class
that annotations kind of expanded and
kind of replaced with the for 500,000
silicates and not really replace so I
mean and the semantics as if is as if it
were replaced yes sure but I mean
Metatron says that is yeah so that's
that's basically one yeah so in a way
you're right it's it's not I mean if you
if you if you come from from the
modeling perspective it's probably
differently okay so so two questions to
finish to finish this one is is there
any story between spring and Scala
because I mean this whole expression
language stuff which basically means you
put your expression language into a
string you have no tool support and I
mean also you talked about this template
stuff which is a kind of closure which
Scala has natively have you thought
about doing a spring dot Scala thing
where you exploit Scala's features to
who makes bring more programmable as
first of all concerning to support for
Yale I'm I would be surprised if we
don't support al in one form or another
in the spring sauce to suit soon or
later which is free so it's a free clip
distribution that you can download
actually I'm not aware of of specific
support for spring in Scala I boot the
other way around
suppose specific support for Scala it's
brain we are whatever I mean some kind
of project that for example allows you
to use templates with higher-order
functions and and that kind of stuff I'm
not aware of such a project
if there is one I'm certainly interested
to hear about it I personally didn't
didn't really dive into scholar that
much and we as a company have bought g21
not long ago so we sort of positioned
ourselves in the groovy grades area
rather than the Scala area but I mean
still if there is any project around I
would certainly love to
about it yes I would I so guys listeners
you know how to reach us teaming se
radio dotnet and I was forwarded to you
great last question spring is an open
source project however there is this big
powerful company behind it so how many
of the spring developers are non spring
source or how does this work I think
recently there was this conflict kind of
thing where spring sauce made certain I
think back fixes
people had to pay for something so
what's the what's the open source story
here well the open saw story is that
spring is an open source project it will
always stay that way and we won't change
the the policy the the license that also
what our CEO rod Johnson has said in in
his block I would argue that if you
think about it one of the hurdles that
open source has to take for usage in
companies is the question where do you
get support if there are just some
people who develop an open source
project and there is no one who can
actually stand up and say ok well we are
going to give you this kind of service
level agreement we are going to support
you in that way it's probably not going
to be easy to use it in a professional
environment this this is not related to
the quality of the open source project
or anything it's not about about whether
this this part will actually be needed
and it's just to blame if you are a big
company that's what it boils down to
exactly and I mean that's also why if
you look at commercial commercial
software or most of the time you have
some kind of support contract there were
some miscommunications in particular
miscommunications about the the
maintenance policy that's already it's
it's more less a year ago um and we
actually changed it as well so let me
give you an idea about what the current
policy says if you look at open source
again at other open source projects it's
quite common for the projects to sort of
go for the next version and invest all
the resources in the next version
and I think that's pretty I mean it it's
completely understandable and it makes a
lot of sense because you want to
innovate and you want to do the new cool
features and so on
however what we what this means in a
professional environment is that you
better go for each and every new version
and you cannot I would argue you cannot
afford that in some cases
I mean operations people will just say
well this is not an option at all we
have to we have to stick to the old
version so what we have done now is we
have a policy in place that says each
version of spring will be supported for
three years and each major version there
will be binary releases for that major
version until the next major version
comes out so if spring 3.0 comes out we
will continue to provide binary versions
for Spring 3.0 as would every any other
open source project as well however the
add-on that we have because of the
commercial support is that you can also
stick to 2.5 and you can get binaries
from us if you have support contract
this you have people pay you for doing
the boring work of keeping the old stuff
alive of actually of just providing
binaries of the old stuff it's all do
and if the the well there are petrol
supplied and of the stuff is updated
constantly and all the changes go into
the open source repository so basically
if you if 3.0 is out and you want to
stick to 2.5 you can stick to two point
five zero calories compile your own
binaries or you pay us and we provide
you a with binaries and those panels by
the way also have also enhance so that
you can get more monitoring informations
and we actually do that using using
inspector a compile time weaving so the
code is compiled using a spec tray and
you get a lot of information about
how many transactions were going on and
and how how long it took for the views
to be rendered and so on and so on okay
then I guess thanks I have a hot phone
yeah you got the show yeah thank you for
having me on the show
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio software engineer
radio is an educational program brought
to you by hillside Europe if you want
more information about the podcast and
all the other episodes visit our website
at se - radio dotnet if you want to
support us you can donate to the AC
radio team by our website or you can
advertise for se radio for example by
clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
links and the slash stop button to
contact the team please send email to
team at SC - radio net or if it is
specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under the
creative comments
2.5 license please see the website for
details thanks to Charlie Crowell and
the portside Music Network for the music
used in this show the song is called
Vegas Achtung